Leah: Mental health concerns can be
painful and traumatic for all of the
family and can have a huge impact
both financially and emotionally.
Also a child or young person’s
mental health problems, can
have real consequences for
others within their family.
When a family member such as a child or
a sibling has mental health concerns, it
can be an extremely stressful time and
may in turn create health problems such as
headaches, loss of appetite, fatigue, and
insomnia for other members of the family.
It may also cause cognitive and emotional
problems such as anxiety, depression,
guilt, anger, fear and confusion or
behavioural troubles such as changes
in attitude, and social withdrawal.
Often family members develop
psychological or social problems of
their own, to such an extent that
they also need help and support.
The consequences of poor mental health in
a family can further compound the mental
health of the child or young person.
If they can see the effects their
mental health is having the family,
such as loved ones becoming upset
and worried about them, they may
try to remove themselves from family
life, so that normality can return.
Children who are too young to fully
grasp the consequences of mental
illness can find it difficult to
understand why their sibling isn't
well or is acting unusually and may
tend to blame themselves and grow up
feeling different, lonely, and isolated.
Ultimately this may lead to others
developing psychological, behavioural,
and social problems of their own.
Family life can become unsettled and
unpredictable causing a family member to
maybe leave their job, give up socialising
or following recreational pursuits.
They may feel nervous about inviting
people into their home and find
it difficult to open up to people
about their relative's problems.
It’s important therefor that we look
at the family as a whole when looking
at the potential knock on problems
connected with Mental Health and look
to provide support options beyond
the immediacy of the person in focus